A Finding Aid to the Burt Chernow Papers, 1930-2002, in the Archives of American Art AAA.cherburt
Archives of American Art
Burt Chernow papers
1930-2002
AAA.cherburt
Archives of American Art
21.8 Linear feet
The papers of Burt Chernow measure 21.8 linear feet and consist mainly of research materials gathered and produced in the course of writing Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography over an extensive period of close contact with the subjects, from the early 1980s until Chernow's death in 1997. Research materials for the biography include photocopies of personal documents of the Christos, hundreds of recorded interviews with Christo, Jeanne-Claude, their family members, and their associates, transcripts of interviews and research on interview subjects, other collected research material compiled chronologically, drafts of the biography written by Chernow, drafts of the biography and its epilogue produced after Chernow's death, and business records related to the book's production, which include significant correspondence with the Christos. Also found are the published German and U.S. editions of the biography, printed materials and photographs related to the book's subject matter, and fabric samples from five of the Christos' projects undertaken during Chernow's association with them. Chernow's career as an art critic, writer, educator, and arts advocate, primarily in Southern Connecticut, is documented in Chernow's other writings, organizational records, printed materials, and photographs.
Chernow, Burt
Arrangement note
Collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Research Material for Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography, 1930-2002 (17.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-17, 23, OV 24)
Series 2: Other Writing, 1962-1999 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 17-19)
Series 3: Organizational Records, 1963-2000 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 19-20, 23, OV 24)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1960-2002 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 20-21, 23)
Series 5: Photographs, 1950-1997 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 21-23, OV 24)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated 2002 by Ann Chernow, the widow of Burt Chernow.
Biographical/Historical note
Burt Chernow was an art historian, writer, educator, collector, and dealer who founded the Housatonic Museum of Art in Bridgeport, Connecticut, and who, upon his retirement from Housatonic Community College, became the authorized biographer of Christo and Jeanne-Claude, which he researched through close contact with the Christos from 1984 until his death in 1997. Although he had not completed the biography when he died, his wife Ann Chernow saw the manuscript through to publication, and the biography, Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography, was first published in Germany in 2000, and then in the United States in 2002.
Born in New York City in 1933, Chernow earned a master's degree in art education at New York University in 1960, and began his career as an art teacher in the Westport, Connecticut public schools, later joining the faculty of the Art Department at the Housatonic Community College, where he eventually became the department's director. He also taught at the Museum of Modern Art, organizing the Children's Art Carnival in Harlem through the museum, and at Silvermine School of the Arts, the A.B.C.D. Arts Center in Bridgeport, Conn., and the Stamford Museum. While on faculty at Housatonic Community College, he began collecting original artworks, mainly through donations directly from the artists, for what eventually became the Housatonic Museum of Art. Over the course of nearly 30 years he amassed over 4000 works for the collection, the largest of its kind for a community college, and remained the museum's Emeritus Director until his death. He remained active in civic arts organizations in Westport as well, where he was a founding member of the Westport Arts Center, served on the Westport Arts Advisory Council, and helped to establish the annual Westport Arts Awards.
Upon his retirement from the Housatonic faculty in 1984, Chernow approached Christo and Jeanne-Claude about becoming their authorized biographer. He had participated in their project Surrounded Islands in Miami in 1983, and had played a role in exhibitions and artist talks by Christo at the Aldrich Museum (1981) and the Wadsworth Atheneum (1978) as well. He and his wife Ann Chernow attended and helped to document the Wrapped Pont Neuf (1985) in Paris, and then visited Christo's family in Bulgaria in 1986. It was after their Bulgarian trip that Christo and Jeanne-Claude agreed to authorize him to write their biography, and Chernow's research began in earnest. He conducted hundreds of interviews with them, their family, and associates, participated in the major large-scale projects that took place between 1985 and 1995, and completed a draft of the biography up to the year 1982 before he died suddenly in 1997. After his death, his wife Ann Chernow saw the biography through to publication. It was published with an epilogue by Wolfgang Volz, the Christos' official photographer, bringing the Christos' story up to date from where Chernow had left off, first in Germany, and later in the United States and Italy.
Chernow wrote many books, catalogs, and articles about other artists as well, including Milton Avery, Francisco Zuniga, Gabor Peterdi, Will Barnet, Jean Woodham, and Lester Johnson, among others, and published and lectured widely on the subjects of art education and public art.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Burt Chernow measure 21.8 linear feet and consist mainly of research materials gathered and produced in the course of writing Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography over an extensive period of close contact with the subjects, from the early 1980s until Chernow's death in 1997. Research materials for the biography include photocopies of personal documents of the Christos, hundreds of recorded interviews with Christo, Jeanne-Claude, their family members, and their associates, transcripts of interviews and research on interview subjects, other collected research material compiled chronologically, drafts of the biography written by Chernow, drafts of the biography and its epilogue produced after Chernow's death, and business records related to the book's production, which include significant correspondence with the Christos. Also found are the published German and U.S. editions of the biography, printed materials and photographs related to the book's subject matter, and fabric samples from five of the Christos' projects undertaken during Chernow's association with them.
Chernow's career as an art critic, writer, educator, and arts advocate, primarily in Southern Connecticut, is documented in Chernow's other writings, organizational records, printed materials, and photographs. Other writings include drafts of articles, lectures, exhibition reviews, and catalog essays, some of which include research material gathered on the subjects. Artists written about by Chernow include Arman, Milton Avery, Barkley Hendricks, Francisco Zuñiga, Lester Johnson, Gabor Peterdi, and Jean Woodham, among many others, and including many Connecticut artists. A recorded interview with Arman, as well as transcripts of multiple interviews with Zuñiga, are filed with these writings. Also found are many writings and lectures related to the value of visual art in public life and in elementary and higher education. Numerous lectures by Chernow about several of the Christos' large-scale projects are also found, one of which, on the Wrapped Reichstag, is recorded on video.
Organizational records document Chernow's involvement in various art education organizations, his years of teaching at Housatonic Community College, his development of the Housatonic Museum of Art collection, and his work with several local arts organizations in Westport, Conn., including the Westport Arts Advisory Council, the Westport Arts Center, the Westport Schools Permanent Art Collection Committee, and the Westport Weston Arts Council. Types of documents found include correspondence, clippings, photographs, flyers, and notes.
Printed material includes many of the books written by Chernow, and monographs and magazines which included essays on specific artists by Chernow. A file of clippings about Chernow spanning his career is also found. Photographs include prints, negatives, and contact sheets, and consist mainly of photographs of artists, many of which were taken by Chernow, and many of which are signed by the artists with a personal note to the Chernows. A handful of personal photographs of the Chernows are also found.
Arman, 1928-2005; Avery, Milton, 1885-1965; Christo, 1935-, Wrapped Reichstag; Christo, 1935-; Hendricks, Barkley L., 1945-; Housatonic Community College. (Bridgeport, Conn.); Housatonic Museum of Art.; Jeanne-Claude, 1935-2009; Johnson, Lester, 1919-2010; Peterdi, Gabor; Westport Schools Permanent Art Collection.; Westport-Weston Arts Council. (Westport, Conn.); Woodham, Jean, 1925-; Zúñiga, Francisco, 1912-1998; Art critics--Connecticut; Art historians--Connecticut; Art--Study and teaching; Authors--Connecticut; Educators--Connecticut; Interviews; Photographs; Sound recordings; Transcriptions; Video recordings
- Research Material for Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography, 1930-2002; Series 1; 17.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-17, 23, OV 24
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 9 subseries.
  1.1: Biographical Materials, 1960-1995
  1.2: Sound Recordings, 1977-1997
  1.3: Transcripts and Subject Files, 1959-1998
  1.4: Chronological Files, 1986-1997
  1.5: Notes and Writings, 1988-2001
  1.6: Business Records, 1968-2002
  1.7: Printed Material, 1960-2002
  1.8: Photographs, 1930-2001
  1.9: Fabric Samples, 1983-1995
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains materials gathered and produced by Burt and Ann Chernow in the course of writing and publishing Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography. Materials include photocopied personal documents of Christo and Jeanne-Claude, recorded interviews with Christo and Jeanne-Claude and their associates created by Chernow, recorded interviews and lectures by Christo produced by others, transcripts of those recordings produced by Chernow, clippings, photographs, and letters related to interview subjects, and files of research material arranged chronologically by Chernow as part of his writing process. Among the many significant interview subjects are Arman, Mary Bauermeister, Leo Castelli, Lynn Hershman, Ray Johnson, Allan Kaprow, Ivan Karp, Albert and David Maysles, Claes Oldenburg, Pierre Restany, Niki de Saint Phalle, Peter Selz, Harry Shunk, Holly Solomon, Saul Steinberg, and Sam Weiner.
  Notes and writings include drafts of the biography written by Burt Chernow and drafts edited posthumously in a process overseen by Ann Chernow. Business records contain correspondence regarding the production and publication of the biography, including significant correspondence between the Chernows and the Christos. Photographs include personal photographs of the Christos and photographs of their projects, installations, and early exhibitions. Fabric samples are from the major projects spanning the years Chernow worked closely with the Christos, from 1983 to 1995. See series descriptions below for further details.
  Because Chernow died before the biography could be completed, much of his research for the period between 1982 and 1997 is not included in the biography, but is rather summarized in an epilogue by the photographer Wolfgang Volz. When he died unexpectedly in 1997, Chernow had only completed work on chapters pertaining to Christo and Jeanne-Claude's lives before he knew them, up to 1982. Documentation of projects executed during Chernow's period of research, Surrounded Islands (1983), the Wrapped Pont Neuf(1985), Umbrellas (1991), and Wrapped Reichstag (1995) is particularly rich, and Chernow did not have a chance to write his chapters on this period before he died. He did, however, write a number of lectures on these subjects, and drafts of these lectures are found in series 2, Other Writings.
  - Biographical Material of the Christo's, 1960-1995; 1.1; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
    Recorded translations seem to have been produced out of sequence, with multiple letters translated on a single tape. They have been arranged chronologically by the date of the original letter as much as possible for ease of access. Reference to a tape inventory number found on each tape is included with each item listing. These numbers were also written on the tapes themselves. Note that the dates in parentheses are the dates of the original documents, and that 1992, the date of the photocopies, is based on query letter from Burt Chernow to Jeanne Claude requesting the copies dated 1992. Additional photographs of Jeanne-Claude's first wedding are found in series 1.8, Photographs.
    Series consists primarily of documents copied from Christo and Jeanne-Claude's personal papers by Burt Chernow, including Christo and Jeanne-Claude's passports, an address book, appointment books (referred to throughout the papers as "agendas") dating from 1961-1995 (not inclusive, with two books for each of the years 1986-1990), Commission offers, family letters, legal documents, and photographs. Chernow used these materials heavily in his writing process, generating lists of trips and contacts made from the appointment books, which were then used as a basis for his research on specific periods of the artists' lives. Except for the 1968 calendar noted as original, all biographical materials are photocopies made by Burt Chernow from the personal records of Christo and Jeanne-Claude.
    In his papers, Chernow identified certain appointment books as belonging to either Jeanne-Claude or Christo, and he labelled certain appointment books "travel agendas." Chernow's labeling of the appointment books has been retained in the inventory of his photocopies, but these labels are in some ways misleading. Some of the appointment books identified as belonging to one or the other actually have notations in more than one hand and must have been shared to some extent, and the appointment books Chernow called "travel appointment books" do not differ substantially from other appointment books not identified as travel-related.
    Letters to Jeanne-Claude in this series include letters from her mother, father, and sister Joyce and are all in French. Legal documents document Jeanne-Claude's divorce from her first husband Philippe Planchon, and are filed with photographs of Jeanne-Claude and Planchot. These documents are also in French, and have been translated by Ann Chernow. One sound cassette with a recording of her translating the documents is also found. Nine letters from Christo written between 1957 and 1961, mostly written to his brother in Bulgarian and French, are found in the form of recorded translations to English by Maria Radicheva, made at the request of Burt Chernow. Letters are mostly to his brother, Anani Javachev. One letter is to his brother and mother, and another is found to his brother and sister-in-law, Maria. Note that paper copies of the original letters are not found in the collection, so the recorded translations are the only extant record of the letters. Commission offers include an extensive file of letters soliciting wrappings for various commercial or promotional purposes, along with Jeanne-Claude's responses to them, all rejected.
    - Passports (1984-1992), circa 1992; Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Address Book (circa 1965), 1992; Photocopy (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jeanne-Claude's Appointment Books (1961, 1963), 1992; 2 photocopied books (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Christo's Appointment Book, 1968; original (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Christo's Appointment Books (1969, 1971, 1972), 1992; 3 photocopied books (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Christo's Travel Appointment Books (1975, 1976), 1992; 2 photocopied books (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Appointment Books (1967-1981), 1992; 15 photocopied books (Box 1, Folder 11-25)
    - Appointment Books (1982-1991), 1992; 15 photocopied books (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
    - Appointment Books (1992-1995), 1996; 4 photocopied books (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
    - Letters, Legal Documents, and Photographs Relating to Jeanne-Claude's Divorce, circa 1995; 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      In French, with translations; includes one sound cassette with Ann Chernow's translations to English
    - Letters to Jeanne-Claude (circa 1970-1976), circa 1992; photocopies (Box 2, Folder 21)
      In French, with translations
    - Recorded Translations of Christo Letters (Box 2)
      - To Anani and Tsveta Javacheff, from Vienna (1957 March 23), 1987; 2 Sound cassettes tapes labeled 188 and 187 (Box 2, Folder 22, Item 1)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Paris (1959 March 2), 1987; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 188; Found on the same cassette as part 1 of 1957 letter to Anani and Tsveta. (Box 2, Folder 22, Item 2)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Vienna (1957 May), 1987; 2 Sound cassettes tapes labeled 192 and 191 (Box 2, Folder 23, Item 1)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Paris (1958 June), 1987; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 192; Found on same cassette as letter to Anani dated 1957 May (Box 2, Folder 23, Item 2)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Paris (1959 November 11), 1987; 2 Sound cassettes tapes labeled 191 and 189; Part 1 found on same cassette as part 2 of letter to Anani from Vienna dated 1957 May (Box 2, Folder 23, Item 3)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Paris (1960 February 26), 1987; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 190; Found on same cassette as letter to Anani from Paris dated 1959 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 24, Item 1)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Paris (1959 May 25), 1987; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 190; Found on same cassette as letter to Anani from Paris dated 1960 February 26 (Box 2, Folder 24, Item 2)
      - To Anani and Marie Javacheff, from Paris (1961 April 23), 1987; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 193; Found on same cassette as letter to Anani from Paris dated 1958 November 21 (Box 2, Folder 24, Item 3)
      - To Anani Javacheff from Paris (1958 November 21), 1987; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 193; Found on same cassette with letter to Anani and Marie dated 1961 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 24, Item 4)
    - Commission Offers, 1983-1986; 1996 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Sound Recordings, 1977-1997; 1.2; 3 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
    Sound recordings are mainly comprised of interviews of the Christos, their family, and their associates conducted by Burt Chernow between 1984 and 1996, in the course of his research for Christo and Jeanne-Claude: A Biography. Chernow wrote the biography chronologically, collecting research for each period of the Christos' lives in sequence, so the early interviews deal mainly with their early years, and later interviews with more recent years. In some cases, the subject content of the interview -- often a place or project name -- is indicated on the tape label, in which case it is noted in the container list. Interviews with associates include other artists, curators, people who worked on the Christos large-scale projects, critics, and others who knew them personally. Among the many significant interview subjects are Arman, Mary Bauermeister, Leo Castelli, Lynn Hershman, Ray Johnson, Allan Kaprow, Ivan Karp, Albert and David Maysles, Claes Oldenburg, Pierre Restany, Niki de Saint Phalle, Peter Selz, Harry Shunk, Holly Solomon, Saul Steinberg, and Sam Weiner.
    In addition to the more formal interviews, a series of impromptu interviews were conducted by Ann and Burt Chernow during the three Christo projects that were executed while Chernow was working on the biography: the Wrapped Pont-Neuf, Umbrellas, and the Wrapped Reichstag. These project-related interviews and recordings were typically made on site with spectators and producers of the projects while they were on view. Also found are lectures, press conferences, broadcast programs, recorded notes, and music, including a 1981 lecture on Christo by Jan Van Der Marck.
    Interviews of Christo by others, and lectures given by Christo which pre-date the period of Chernow's research, are filed at the end of the series. Some were recorded off the air, and others were recorded by Chernow or other attendees to the appearances. Some appear to have been copied from original recordings, and the sound quality is poor. Two musical recordings associated with Christo projects are also found in the series, including a protest song about "Surrounded Islands," and music composed for the Japanese installation of "Umbrellas."
    Chernow's research was conducted chronologically, that is, Chernow collected information about each period of their lives and then wrote his first draft of that portion of the biography before moving on to the next period. The interviews reflect this process, with earlier interviews covering earlier periods of the artists' lives, and later interviews covering later periods as each section was researched and written.
    Most of the interviews have partial transcripts in series 1.3, which were created by Burt Chernow. The transcripts typically contain summarized portions, with only the portions Chernow found most salient to his research transcribed. The recordings in this series, then, are a unique record of the complete interviews that took place. Recorded conversations with Jeanne-Claude regarding corrections to Chernow's drafts of the biography, created in 1995-1997, do not have typically have transcripts. See series 1.3 for more details.
    Interviews with Christo and Jeanne-Claude are filed chronologically at the beginning of the series, and interviews with others about the Christos follow, filed alphabetically by name. Occasionally interviews from both of these categories are found on the same tape, and cross-references are provided in the inventory. For recordings made during the Pont-Neuf project (Sept 1985), the Umbrellas project (October 1991), or the Reichstag project (June 1995), cassettes are filed by project, with cross-references to subjects of the project-specific interviews found in the alphabetical inventory list. The collected interviews and lectures (1977-1984) are filed chronologically. Although the tape inventory created by Ann Chernow that came with the collection does not seem to follow any logical sequence, inventory numbers written on the tapes are included in the container list to facilitate access to the physical tapes in the collection.
    Additional sound recordings include spoken translations of Christo letters to family in series 1.1, Biographical Materials, a spoken history of the biography project by Ann Chernow, found in series 1.6, Business Records, and an interview with Arman for an article about the artist from 1993, found in series 2, Other Writings.
    - Interviews with Christo and Jeanne-Claude (Box 3)
      - Christo, on Bulgaria, 1984 November 27; 1 Sound cassettes duplicate, tape labeled 206; 1 Sound cassettes original, tape labeled 19 (Box 3, Folder 1, Item 1)
      - Jeanne Claude, 1985 January 16; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 18 (Box 3, Folder 1, Item 2)
      - Christo, 1985 September 22-24 (Box 3)
        See Interviews with Other Subjects by Project, Pont Neuf Wrapped, of same dates.
      - Jeanne-Claude, 1985 December 25; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 17 (Box 3, Folder 1, Item 3)
      - Ivan Karp on Christo, 1986 February 28; 1 Sound cassettes tape labeled 16 (Box 3, Folder 1, Item 4)
        Found on same cassette as part I of Christo Interview of the same date
      - Christo on Prague to Paris, 1986 February 28; 2 Sound cassettes original tapes labeled 16, 15; 2 Sound cassettes duplicate, tapes labeled 207, 208 (Box 3, Folder 1, Item 5)